# **JAMIN ALI**

+447551550332 j.ali@keele.ac.uk 4 Cauldon road Stoke-On-Trent, UK, St42ed

#### **SUMMARY**

I am a Final year Ph.D. student working in the lab of Prof Toby Bruce at Keele University, United Kingdom. My research focuses on exploiting the chemical ecology of insect-plant tritrophic interaction, induced plant defence to sustainably manage phytophagous insect pests and minimize crop losses.

## PUBLICATIONS: PAPERS/BOOKS/BOOK CHAPTERS

Ali, J., Covaci A., Roberts, M. J. Sobhy I. S., Kirk, W. and Bruce, T. J. A., Effects of cis- Jasmone treatment of brassicas on interactions with Myzus persicae aphids and their parasitoid Diaeretiella rapae, Frontiers in plant science, doi: 10.3389/fpls.2021.711896

Ali, J., Bruce, T. J.A., Sobhy, I. S., and (2021). Wild species of potato as potential sources of resistance against the aphid Myzus persicae. Journal of Pest Management Science, (Paper due for submission)

Sobhy, I. S., Ali, J., and Bruce, T. J.A., (2021). Manipulating plant defense against Insect herbivores using defence elicitors: a review. Journal of Frontiers in Plant Science, (Abstract accepted)

Mohammad Mukarram, Sadaf Choudhary 1, Mo Ahamad Khan, Palmiro Poltronieri, M. Masroor A. Khan, Ali, J., Daniel Kurjak and Mohd Shahid (2021). Lemongrass essential oil components with antimicrobial and anticancer activities. Journal of Cells MDPI, (Under review)

## TEACHING AND RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

## DEMONSTRATION:

School of life Science, Keele University, UK (Sep 2019- To date)

TEACHING: Volunteer teacher at community school, Beresford, Stoke-on-Trent, UK (Jan 2019 - June 2019)

PROJECT COMPLETED: Collection and Identification of Ants around the A.M.U. Campus Aligarh, India.

### REVIEWER

Journal of Entomologia Generalis (Peer reviewed; Impact Factor; 5.6), Germany ACHIEVEMENTS

THE GRADUATE APTITUDE TEST IN ENGINEERING (GATE) 2018

Department of Higher Education, Ministry of Human Resources Development (MHRD), Government of India.

### **OVERSEAS SCHOLARSHIP (2017)**

National Overseas Scholarship for Ph.D. in abroad. Funding Agency; Government of India.

#### **UGC-JRF (2016)**

CSIR-University Grant Commission of India.

#### **EDUCATION**

#### **KEELE UNIVERSITY, STAFFORDSHIRE, UK**

(8th May 2018 to date)

Ph.D. (Applied Entomology) student, Supervisor: **Prof Toby Bruce** (Chemical Ecology) **Ph.D. Title:** The chemical ecology of a model aphid pest, Myzus persicae, and its natural enemies

#### ALIGARH MUSLIM UNIVERSITY, INDIA

(2008-2016)

Master of Science in Zoology (Entomology) 2016 Bachelor of Science in Zoology (Hons.) 2014 Senior secondary school 2011

#### **CONFERENCES/ WORKSHOPS**

#### International

Jamin Ali, Joe Roberts, David Buss, Islam S. Sobhy and Toby Bruce, *cis-Jasmone induced defence: from Arabidopsis to commercial Brassicas,* (Oral Presentation), PG Forum, Royal Entomological Society 21-22 March 2019, University of York, UK

**Jamin Ali**, Joe Roberts and Toby Bruce, *cis*-Jasmone induced defence: from *Arabidopsis* to commercial *Brassicas*, (Poster presentation) 10<sup>th</sup> May, FNS Symposium, Keele University, (2019) UK

Jamin Ali, Joe Robert and Toby Bruce, Wild species of potato as potential sources of resistance against Myzus persicae, (Poster presentation) 20-21 November 2019, Association of Applied Biologists, Conference: Advances in Biological Control and IPM 2019: Addressing the innovation crisis, Lincolnshire, UK

Insect Chemical Ecology Workshop (ICE-2019), PhD-level course in insect Chemical Ecology, 10-21 June 2019, Nairobi, Kenya

Jamin Ali, Joe Roberts and Toby Bruce. Resistance of wild potato species against Myzus persicae. International Congress Entomology, Helsinki, Finland-2020, (Postponed due to COVID-19) (Abstract Accepted).

EPS workshop 'Plant-Insect interactions' Thursday 21 October 2021' at the WICC hotel, Wageningen, The Netherlands.

#### **CERTIFICATE/TRAINING**

Introduction to Teaching & Demonstrating (ITAD)

Scientific Writing course (4 weeks-online)

Academic English for Postgraduate Science Students

Research design and data analysis using SPSS/R

Science leadership workshop, CPU, India

Workshop on Microbial Genomics (Online)

Certificate: How to secure funding?

Certificate in German Language

What to expect from the Certified Peer Reviewer Course?

Safeguarding Training Awareness Workshop-Faith and Community Groups (Stoke-On-Trent

Safeguarding Children Board)

## **MEMBERSHIPS**

Indian Entomological Society, India

Indian National Science Congress, India

Royal Entomological Society, UK

International Society of Chemical Ecology (ISCE)

#### **SKILLS**

Problem-solving skills

Critical thinking skills

Project management skills

## **LANGUAGES**

Hindi

Urdu

**English** 

German (Beginner level)

### **REFERENCES**

<sup>\*\*</sup>Available upon request